and this is also another talk uh in the
general area of
ranking you may have noticed it's always
like there's some kind of theme for this
session it's almost like I've we've
grouped talks together um anyway very
pleased to welcome Martin and Katarina
from Ox group um Maron is a senior
machine learning engineer ox
and Karina is a junior data scientist
they're going to be co-presenting
today um and they're going to be talking
about an army of
models if you got learning to rank and
you've got lots of different potential
models how do you train an army of
models so please put your hands together
for Katarina and
marsid hi uh good morning I think I hope
you are hearing me fine and I hope you
still handle one more presentation
before lunch break but let that at least
we have that to look forward to uh today
Martin and I will be talking about the
learning to rank framework and how we
leverage it to create an army of models
but first we would like to briefly
introduce ourselves so I'm Kina I'm from
o which is a small town in the south of
Portugal the algar so if you like good
weather and even better food I strongly
advise you to visit uh in 2017 I did my
bachelors and then later my masters in
computer science and engineering focused
mainly on data science and machine
learning and last year I joined OLX as a
data scientist traine uh and was later
promoted to Junior data scientists now
I'll pass the mic to
Marin thanks uh first of all uh I'm
happy to be here uh I'm Martin I'm uh
from po9 in
Poland uh from the city which has a
really beautiful uh City Hall with the
on the Old Market Square and also and
Paul and we are quite famous from uh of
the S Martin crosson which I really
recommend to tast when you are in POS I
also finished a bachelor and Masters in
uh computer science uh almost 10 years
ago at the pan University of Technology
and currently I work in a ear group
where I've been there for seven years
and I'm was always working with search
ranking
recommendations so that's that's about
me
but I would like to introduce uh our
team that worked on the the project that
we will talk about today especially Ilan
Dua uh one of our main contributors to
the
code uh also Katarina Vagner bisa our
product manager and last but not least
Christian Martinez who
is uh with us uh at the end of the stage
so uh we can we can represent uh our
team I will go uh quickly through agenda
uh
so as you know we will talk about the
army of models and to understand this
topic I think it's crucial to
understand uh who we
are then I will go quickly through
through learning to rank algorithm
because like uh today uh we had a few uh
explanation about it but we will
introduce you with the oix use
case uh then I will tell you a bit of
the main challenges not all but the main
challenges that we face during the
implementation of this
algorithm and uh the rest of the
presentation will be focused on the
solution status quo and at the end uh we
can start discussion at
Q&A so we are O's
group and this is the name of the
company
that contains like possess multiple
platforms of classified ads classified
and starting from Real Estate classified
jobs
classified autom M classified so bunch
of different platforms also there are
platforms which
are uh collecting all of these types
together and we are in
Europe across many countries uh starting
from Portugal
Poland also part of Asia Kazakhstan or
usbekistan
so at least we have uh 13 of those
platforms uh in our
portfolio and one common thing for for
them uh except that that the text taret
it's sometimes it's different but the
common thing is like we have ranked the
listings learning to rank algorithm
so uh I know that uh for my majority of
the audience this might be common but
there might be people who uh that the
topic is is new for them so I will go
quickly through the Practical uh example
and explain how it works uh in in our
environment
so learning to rank is algorith where
the goal is to create learning to rank
model the input of the learning to rank
model basically there are two two inputs
the
context of the
search and also the list of items
documents in this example the context is
just the query iPhone 128
gab with this query we extract documents
from the search engine and we have
default uh default list of ranked uh
items but this ranked items might not be
ideal to especially to meet some uh
business
targets so to when we provide those two
inputs to our learning to rank model the
goal of this model is to rank them to
meet new targets that will satisfy our
business or the satisfy satisfy our uh
users yeah
Works no yeah
and at the end yeah the output will be
the new rank
document so right now like how we can uh
how could we build the data set to train
such
model I think uh at the first
presentation we we saw a bit uh but
right now to coming back to our reality
right we could ask our us
users all right sure
[Music]
okay okay I hope that was
smooth all right so we we could ask our
uh our users
right based on the query I know that
might not be visible uh there is a query
iPhone 15 Pro uh we could ask like is it
relevant for you right and then we will
get an answers
uh yes or no or like uh the the what's
the uh what's
the relevancy for for our users
but in our reality it's expensive it's
expensive it's time consuming and also
tedious for our users
[Music]
so we we uh don't go this way it's not a
solution that we want and also like uh
this is what
uh we talked about uh previously in the
different presentations that we could
rely on users signals to create this
user signals we base on the in our uh
use case clickstream uh events so
basically tracking of our
users on our listings uh we have uh
several uh signals starting from
clicking on the title on the listing on
the item uh some of our classifi they
have a delivery option so when there is
a a click on a delivery option it's a
quite quite uh strong signal also we
have a add to favorites another signal
that uh is strong but also even that
contacting with our sellers this could
be to to find the the strong user
signals so as you see we don't have a
single relevance signal but multiple
them and sometime we have sometimes we
have to uh twak those or merge them or
combine as a
one so how we build right so we start
from query uh ID uh in our data set
then we follow up with the document
IDs of the of
the IDS that we have in our
database and then features and this is
one of
the trickest part in the in the data
set here I will give you some examples
which are starting from ad Price which
is like pretty uh easy to get we call it
like static features because like we
already have it in our
databases also at freshness this is for
how long our uh ad uh was posted in the
in the in the listing so kind of a
document
recency uh and it might uh be understood
like if it's if it's like so not so like
is it uh for how long it is on the
platform so if it's longer then it might
mean that okay it's it's not a good item
for for our users and also this is very
uh good feature in our case because it
shows kind of popularity but it's very
hard
to uh to get the search engine which is
like click click through rate and we
call it like Dynamic features so I just
show you only three uh features but in
general we have more than
10 and at the end we have some relevancy
scores so the the things that I
mentioned in the previous
slides in oix usual LTR pipeline uh
looks like this that we have to start
from some data leg which in our case
it's s3e and then we have a two options
how we build our data sets we use trino
it's a SQL query uh um
solution built on top of S3 and also
Apache spark for big data processing and
uh they they can give us the data set
everything is scheduled by airflow and
then we for different platforms we use
different libraries different libraries
for training a model it might be XG
boost it might be cut boost and it might
be uh light GBM or maybe in the future
we'll have other
approaches uh the output of the training
model uh job will go to model registry
for that we use
mlflow uh where we consume our models to
use in experiments to an AB testing and
finally it goes to one of the search
engines in our case it's a
solar now I will go through uh three
challenges uh that we uh faced with the
implementation of learning to rank and
uh I will try to show you the motivation
for the
project first Challenge and I think like
people who work in e-commerce uh this
will this topic might be
uh similar to what you have on your
platforms is like listings are not uh
monolitic uh we can have like two or
even three listings at the same listing
so what I mean the first part of the
listing right is uh pay dos so basically
ads that were paid to be at the top and
we can treat it as a independent listing
then we have a organic ads these are
free ads that uh were posted by our
users and and also in our case uh we
have
a another Pro promo promoting option for
our users to bump up ads so kind of
boosting at the top but this boosting
it's not like you go just through uh few
positions up but you go at the top
because it's based on the uh created uh
time stamp also we have other Target
that we could optimize which is delivery
delivery ad and it's as you can see not
for ads on the listing uh at some point
in our
business uh
management they wanted to boost delivery
ads
uh uh to and to not harm V uh the the
paid paid
ads uh how we can tackle this problem is
to we we used multiobjective
optimization and uh for that we want to
optimize
uh few targets right at the same time
and to maximize like the the sum of them
the sum of these of these two Targets
and on the Y AIS we have the pay dots n
dcg on the x axis we have a three
ads and here these blue points are
trained
models uh and our goal in the
multiobjective optimization is to find
so-called parto line or frontal line uh
and by
moving uh moving on this
line we can decide what tradeoff we are
able to accept in our business because
uh we could optimize for organic but but
then we will lose uh Revenue so we we
could ask our uh business right what's
the tradeoff that you are going to
accept another challenge and this is uh
I
think main challenge uh to understand
why we need an army of
models in this example we have a one
platform oix this platform is like for
all types of classified we have one
country uh here with at category
Electronics in our
experiment uh we saw that models
performed
better uh when they are trained on a
specialized categories so we don't have
one General model model right for one
platform or for one country but we tend
to train models per category
because Targets in those categories
might differ so for example in
electronics where we have a ads with
deliveries we might want to increase the
deliveries ads and the
listing so and then also we train by
different type of a search we differ a
search by keyword search so basically
with the token right or category brows
browsing where we only use filters or
and uh filters of I know price filters
of
location uh or
category and every every this type of
the of the searches can have different
targets so for this example we have four
models for examp uh for models and but
that's not the the end
right we have several
uh
platforms uh to uh to support at least
seven countries for every platform and
at least or about right 18 categories of
the first level of the category
three so I didn't wanted to show you the
whole uh whole uh Cate whole uh tree but
you can imagine how many models at some
point we need
another challenge is the pipeline hell
and it's mostly the hell for our data
Engineers to maintain maintain uh those
pipelines every platform has a slightly
different sometimes it's slightly
sometimes it's like highly different uh
data schema so uh so our uh
input differs a lot and we have to
always like to to make them accessible
for the
training uh and then deploy it
so we quickly realize that the we clone
some part of the pipelines and some part
of the pipelines are uh different
basically it created a technical that uh
very very
fast so at some point in our team we ask
that question right can we do better
and we uh by this Square we find out
that okay this place this part can be uh
can be
replaced so our main motivation for the
LTR framework that we uh uh created were
like first to stop duplicating efforts
uh for for teams across
platforms stop uh growing the technical
Deb uh and basically cloning the code
which is uh bad
smell also we noticed that our data
scientists uh was they were Reinventing
the wheel uh sometimes
so we wanted to create the Synergy
between them when they can when when
where they can work all together also
for our product uh was very important
right to uh bring features more often
right so to increase the AB testing uh
time uh this will uh this was this was
their requirement and also from
engineering
right bringing all together
uh building one platform we could reduce
cost or at least we could monitor this
cost better and then reduce
them so LTR framework this is the
solution that
we brought uh to tackle those uh those
problem that I uh showed you before but
first yeah this is the place
where we uh can replace right the the
part of data pre-processing the part of
the training of the
models even maybe at some point the the
part of deploying but for now it's it's
uh not included in the framework also
inference this is the part where we
cannot
uh we cannot replace currently because
every
platform has a slightly different
approach of serving those models
sometimes it's
a a solar right ay solar sometimes it's
a external uh reranking uh service so
outside the search engine or maybe at
some point one of the platforms will
decide okay maybe we'll go to uh open
search right or uh elastic
search first thing that we did to make
it happen the to implement the framework
was to established data set unification
so kind of standard for our teams that
uh the data set need to follow the the
requirements right so the first part
it's uh query ID right d ID the
identification of the ad in our case
rank which might not be always uh needed
but because of our all our our platforms
uh they they have this information we
decided okay it it will be also required
then we have a set of features with the
prefix F and our uh
tables where we could easily def uh find
right what's the what's the feature
what's not and we need at least one uh
the same with the relevant signals and
usually you have one signal of relevance
like combined together in this case we
decided okay at this level we don't want
to combine right but we will do it uh
like just before training and this will
be the decision of our data scientists
or maybe later on like of our business
managers
right so we we wanted to have this
option uh available also some extra
columns uh which are more like
technical uh part and
partition uh partitions uh also
technical uh part of the data set these
might be used for our data scientists to
prepare some analysis and so on at the
bottom there is an example uh with the
how this data set could look
like one of the main points of the
framework was a configuration right we
have to train multiple models but uh I
think I'll pass this over to Katarina uh
to talk about and go you through through
the
topic uh so complimenting everything
Martin said from the motivation to the
actual framework and considering that we
have three different units for OLX core
Motors and real estate and each unit
operates in at least three different
countries up to seven and that we
experiment in different environments
from production to staging and
considering that we have at least one
model and each model can have at least
one target definition it will be a big
mess of a configuration folder so we
will be swamped with different
configuration files for different units
so we wanted to increase our flexibility
enhance experimentation and of course
achieve better organization when setting
up our configuration so that's why we
chose to use idra hyra is an open source
Tool uh and we decided it has several
key features but we decided to explore
it today a bit in the ones that we
really use on a daily basis so the first
one is its hierarchical configur uration
so this kind of works as like modules uh
so we will be able to create your own
configuration parts and pick and choose
when you are um setting up your
configuration files so you are reusing
existing configuration parts so take it
in consideration this really small
example as you can see there's this
default section and each value inside is
a folder that is created on your
configuration file and the value that
you specify is a file that you've
already created with everything that you
need uh for that given process so
environment you can have for development
and production you can have different
model types that require different
combinations and of course different
targets and Brands and countries so
imagine that you for specific unit you
use a model type but you want to try a
different one you just change it so if
your file is is already created you
don't need to copy paste the whole
configuration file and you just can
import what is already done the same
thing applies if you want to change your
target or if you want to change the
brand and if you want to add an
evaluation a new folder in your configur
ation and same thing applies and you can
just try and explore the different
combinations and add new ones to your
configuration so at the end of the day
you'll be able to use your modules and
create your configuration files without
having to really uh replicate code and
have it very organized so you will use
the you will take advantage of this
organization setup to be able to reuse
for your different units uh but of
course you're already stuck with this
specific uh default configuration for
given units so another feature is the
runtime command line override so this
allows you to override existing Fields
append or remove new ones which give us
some flexibility and as well D allow us
to perform Dynamic adjustments if we
want to perform like some changes and
experiment on development St development
staging or either production so imagine
that this is how we join our model so
python minus M uh and you imagine that
you the default code is for Real Estate
and you want to try for a different unit
and for a configuration file that you've
created so you just need to override it
here and then it will run run with the
new configuration the same thing applies
if you want to test out a different
environment you just change it here or
if you want to append uh a new value a
new field or remove those but of course
your code needs to first uh be able to
handle these changes uh we really take
advantage of this even inside our
pipeline so you are not really
committing to these changes you won't
need to change your default
configurations and you can just
experiment and of course if you want to
keep track of the experiments that youve
did Adra also has a logging history and
you can also store the final uh
configuration file so now that we have
configuration and data set how is the
deployment working so Marchin PR showed
you how the deployment looked and this
is how we currently have it in the
framework so we push the changes to our
repository this changes uh trigger our
cicd pipelines that if run successfully
will uh reflect those changes in our
airflow uh pipeline so where we fetch
the data either from trino and Spark as
Marchin uh as previously explained and
where we train our model and now a new
part is ylabs monitoring and also ml
flow Which comp both combine represent
our monitoring current setup and finally
the model that is trained is then sent
to solar which will then be used in
production but so the big major
difference here is our monitoring part
and the current setup is we fetch the
data we process it we log this
information to wabs then we train the
model and the remaining information is
stored either in wabs andl flow for
different purposes but why did we choose
this combination I think it's worth
mentioning and go through brief briefly
from each other platform so wabs uh if
you're not aware it's kind of partially
open sourced uh but it has several key
features from data quality observation
to model performance and it also allows
us to have customizable dashboard so in
our case we can have different
dashboards for different units and we
can customize it and tailor it to each
unit's needs uh of course we can also
detect any anomalies that might be
happening but most importantly it
supports ranking model so it has
functionality to calculate uh metric
ranking metrics and other ranking
related uh process so as you can see we
have uh taken advantage of these
customizable dashboards and we have
specified a nomenclature and we divided
each dashboard between real estate and
Country so we are looking at real EST uh
real estate sorry unit country so we
will have real estate for all the
different countries and of course Motors
and OLX this allows us to have a better
project organization and improve model
reliability and reduce down time because
we are easily notified of where the
problems are happening in which country
and unit so this is an overview of what
the dashboards look like so these little
boxes are called widgets and they are
also customizable and you can remove
those and we have like an overview of
our current data how many data we have
logged all the input Health the model
performance we have also anomaly summary
and monitoring coverage which is also a
big part of why we lose ylabs because we
can set up your uh own monitors so you
can create them V via their UI Builder
or enabling default ones or you can also
create your owns um from scratch so
custom ones are also available uh but so
as you can see in the UI Builder uh not
very clear here I'm sorry but you can
create monitors for data drift uh data
quality data model performance as well
either from the yabs ranking metrics
that they calculate or from your own
custom ones and you can specify like the
thresholds everything that are supposed
to um calculate and compare on the when
the monitors run but most importantly
what actions should be performed in case
any anomaly pops up so in our case we
have a dedicated slack Channel where we
receive this information where as you
can see we chose to receive a summary uh
of the anomalies that happen in a given
monitor in a given dashboard but you can
receive one for each anomaly you can
specify at your own needs and also
receive it in email and if you're like
on Focus mode and you're not really
aware of your slack messages you can
also view your dash board in the wab
setup and you have an overview of the
anomalies in the the the specified time
frame and as well if you U over you can
understand if it was Data drift problem
a quality problem or either
performance and to complement wabs of
course we have ml flow but it's more
tailored to the units and the model
itself so we keep track of our
experiments we are able to store our
models and of course reproduce them if
we like to as you can see you specify a
a run name and then you have model
information so the parameters used for
your model the metrics achieved and the
tags so tags you can put anything you'd
like so either like the developer that
ran this experiment to the used features
and finally the artifacts which are you
can store any given file that you think
is needed so we we we store in our case
the model files the configuration
because we as I said before we take
advantage of hyra or command line
override in our pipelines so the final
configuration is stored here so we can
understand what we actually experiment
with and finally the model cards uh
model cards are a PDF file that in Ox we
decided to create uh because it's like
an English summary of what the model
achieved so it's an easy way to explain
to non tech people what you actually uh
what actually was the impact of your
model so we have data set insights
ranking insights uh all written in a way
that you can easily understand okay was
this worth it or not uh and we also
complement it with different
visualizations in our case with SH with
shapely values and if you're not aware
uh this give you information about the
importance of the feature that you used
uh actually have in your model so it's
really helpful for non-tech people
especially RPMs so that they can
understand uh if the changes were
actually worth it or not so now that the
framework is ready what is actually the
status quo of the project so as we said
we have three different units for real
estate in all the countries that we
operating uh we are already integrated
in the framework so it's already
operating in there and we are about 30%
in uh integrating OLX score for all the
seven different countries so all of this
combined represen in 10 different
learning to rank models which I think we
can already call it a good army to have
in in the project and finally we will
have Motors in all of these combin we
will really start increasing um our
army uh but what does this actually mean
the releases like integrating them in
case of real estate uh we have for
Storia autodom and Imo virtu the three
different uh uh countries we operating
we have automated Pipeline and the
monitoring setup both ml flow and wabs
so the daily pipelines they they create
data set creation daily and of course
model training and we have one for each
country we're operating so we are able
to understand if it run successfully for
each country or not and if we have the
data for for that day and if the model
trains
successfully then for ML flow as I
previously mentioned after training if
the success if the training was
successful
we keep track of our models of features
parameters anything that we like and of
course the model cards and for wabs uh
we have a dashboard for each country so
for Real Estate we have the three
different dashboards and within wild
laabs we are able to compare each
dashboard and the metric so we are we
don't we are not losing them by
separating in different countries it's
also very helpful to understand what
what is working and how everything is
being
impacted but are we actually helping
someone so all of this to say uh with
all of this combined we have estimated
that it takes us about we are 70% 5%
faster when adding a new feature to a
data set and considering the entire
process so from calculating it to
training a model with this new feature
we're about 25% faster and just looking
at training a single model it takes us
depending on the unit about 50 to 75%
faster this is our our estimations so
taking in consideration this impact and
what Martin had previously talked about
our motivation uh we stop duplicating
efforts we add Synergy to our LTR pro
project and of course it's a lot more
faster as I previously talked which I
think it's pretty pretty pretty
impressive so now that we are happy with
the outcome of the framework what are
like the next steps there's always place
to grow and we will continue migrating
our unit so finishing o xcore and adding
Motors and then we will take advantage
of having all of these projects within a
single place and try to understand if
what's actually works for a unit might
as well work for my my use case as well
and continue to accommodate growth and
short performance and of course
monitoring production which is something
that we've talked about considering that
OLX score has several models currently
in production and because we do really
believe in our project and the quality
and it's really helpful why not just you
know open source it it's just a goal we
have in mind so if it's ready to open
source then it's ready for everyone to
use it's great quality project so that
concludes our presentation I hope you
guys can resonate with this little
illustration if not just feel free to
ask any
questions wonderful thank you Marin and
Karina so we're going to go some Quest
oh they've gone up quickly Keen we have
the first one
here yeah thank you first for the very
nice talk um I saw that you mentioned
like three implementations of boosted
trees um did you measure somehow like
what the advantages of One Versus the
other are whether you need all three or
uh yeah thank you uh for the question uh
it's more like we created a technical de
at the beginning and uh these libraries
uh come from U different units right so
uh it's not like we tested in a one uh
unit all of three but sometimes yeah we
tested two right but another one uh
comes from the another unit our goal was
like to give an option right for our
data scientist to the site right if you
want to like GBM right because your uh
features are uh more suitable uh for
that model then go there so uh it's we
didn't test uh all of them compared
together it was like more motivation to
give an option to our data data
scientist to the
site thank you um okay so we got a
question from our online audience uh
deata asks uh what aspect of the model
retraining in ml flow takes care of data
drift uh in terms of dynamic change in
product features or product
anomalies this is a uh really good
question and I'm not sure that I'm uh
able to uh
answer this pre precisely because
uh we on on some platforms we observe
this data drift uh especially for
automotive when where you have a kind of
seasonality but for example on a
platforms with Goods this data
drift it's supposed to be right but we
in fact we don't observe uh sometimes uh
it's a it's um
season of Christmas right and there is a
different be behavior in U in features
especially uh we are still
learning uh for sure in our plans is
like to create reoccurring trainings but
to decide right what's the best period
of training right we still we are still
not there maybe at some point right we
decide okay if the data drift is below
some level then trigger the training and
automatically deploy great thank you
next question so
here thanks for the nice talk uh this
question about is about multiobjective
optimization right uh specifically uh
it's easily easy to come up with
training labels for relevance right but
it's very difficult to come up with uh
training labels when you want to have
this Pito optimal setup so it has
implications in not only coming up with
training labels but also offline
evaluation M what do you actually use to
as training labels to train this
multiobjective optimization or learning
to rank first secondly what's your
offline evaluation setup thanks so uh
about
labels how we label the like to re uh
rephrase your question how do we uh
label our data
uh we use uh our tracking uh data so we
use what we have already on the platform
I was explaining that we have this user
signals right uh so we don't create a
judgment list
but we know as well that would be good
to combine two right judgment list and
also the data that we already have we
are still not there this is in plans
also with the we can leverage on a gen
and one of the our project esec
especially in jobs we uh see that gen
could be helpful to create a judgment
list so maybe we'll go there trying to
answer your second question uh about
offline evaluation metrics for that uh
we have uh a few first one is uh our
offline metrics uh of ndcg after the
training uh of the model and also of the
data set and another one is the waps and
waps we didn't show that but recently
waps uh added this option for ranking
metrics where you have a buil in set of
metrics like mdcg
map uh bunch of stuff also with
different K
positions uh and in our case it's
important to not only measure ndcg for
the whole listing but ndcg for pay dos
for Organics which are free and for
example this delivery as so different
different uh metrics but uh I don't know
if this answers your
question thank you so we got time for
one last question
uh thank you very much for nice
presentation
uh speaking about Army of models have
you tried uh to uh make it more or less
granular how do you decide what is the
right level of granularity which is
country plus category right
now uh oh this is a good question no no
we didn't experiment uh no we did
experiment like we had first we start
from the general model right one per
platform
but then
uh s we see uh we saw that in some
categories we don't perform well but for
on some categories we perform very well
so we decided okay can we do better and
we just we will just train the mo
another model on one category but the
rest of the categories will uh will be
served by this General model so yeah the
experiment uh AB testing showed that
yeah this specialized model for one
category like we boosted the the the
metrics that are we are interested in
significantly but yeah the question is
like where is the line right uh to that
we don't want to cross and to be honest
I don't I don't
know
uh also this will be kind of trade-off
uh between business and us right because
more models for us means like more
work uh for
business every category would like to
have home because they will get more
money from them so still to this is the
place to
experiment thank you very much and uh
please do thank our lovely presenters